<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To all people that profess the eternal truth of the living God this is a true and real demonstration of the cause why I have denied and do deny the authority of George Fox ...</title>
            <author>Harwood, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29869</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11216458</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11216458</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46848</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46848)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1444:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To all people that profess the eternal truth of the living God this is a true and real demonstration of the cause why I have denied and do deny the authority of George Fox ...</title>
                  <author>Harwood, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 [i.e. 7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: John Harwood.</note>
                  <note>"This is only to go amongst Friends in all countreys, nations and islands where George Fox's Papers of enmity against the innocent hath passed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fox, George, 1624-1691. --  Papers of enmity against the innocent.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46848:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TO ALL PEOPLE That profeſs the Eternal TRUTH OF THE living GOD, THIS IS A true and real demonſtration of the cauſe why I have denied, and do deny the Authority of <hi>George Fox;</hi> which is the original ground of the difference betwixt us, whatſoever may be pretended or deceitfully alledged againſt me; which I do in ſimplicity deſire Friends to peruſe impartially, and weigh in the ballance of Equity, that they may clearly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern, and ſenſibly feel the depth of the ground of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in difference betwixt us, that ſo none may be blinded through falſe pretences or vain reports, but that every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular in <hi>Iſrael</hi> may ſee and perfectly know the Truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they judge of this matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is only to go amongſt Friends in all Countreys, Nations and Iſlands where</hi> George Fox<hi>'s Papers</hi> of <hi>Enmity againſt the innocent hath paſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46848:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends in truth,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I proceed to ſignifie the ſeveral cauſes which I believe and know to be the chiefeſt ſubſtantial matter of the ground of <hi>George Fox</hi>'s diſowning of me, and warning Friends of me, I ſhall in the living truth open my heart, and unſold my breaſt innocently and nakedly unto you, concerning this particular: That the truth of God manifeſt amongſt Friends, I never did, neither do I diſown, God is my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but in the fear of the pure God I declare it. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes and own that there is no other truth or way of ſalvation but what hath been, and is manifeſt amongſt Friends that abide in their meaſures of living knowledge given of God; neither did I ever or forſake Friends Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, though ſuch things may be falſly charged againſt me; but this I do teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie unto you in the name and truth of God, that <hi>G. F.</hi> and ſome of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants have endeavoured to ſhut me our from amongſt you, both by their revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling words and writings, ſuppoſing thereby to take away the ſtrength of the teſtimony of truth God in his mercy hath manifeſted in me, as alſo to keep him from owning publike judgement for theſe crimes and capital offences hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mentioned and charged againſt him, which ſubtile evaſions in the Light of truth and righteouſneſs is ſeen and diſowned, and as he hath cauſed others to confeſs and acknowledge their offences, and to own publike judgement for them, according to his own Law and Rule he ought to do the ſame, and this is no other but really according to the Law of Equity, to try a man by his own Law, or meaſure him by his own Rule; ſo that to call him to an account for his offences, as he hath called others, is juſt and righteous before God &amp; juſt men, it is but the ſame meaſure he hath meaſured to others, (at may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved which is meaſured to him again; and many, or the moſt part of theſe things which are now charged againſt him, hath been charged upon him two years ago, and ſeveral of his own boſom-friends nominated to have the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, as <hi>Iohn Bolton, Gerard Roberts, Gilbert Laytie,</hi> and ſeveral others whom I deſired might have the examination and tryal of theſe things, and judge of them according as they found them, in, and by the <hi>law</hi> of truth and righteouſneſs, which he hath hitherto neglected and refuſed, which is a ſignal teſtimony that he acknowledgeth himſelf guilty of them; for he that is clear from guilt, need not fear the judgement of truth; but|the guilty ſtarts aſide, and he hides himſelf from judgement; but I know that judgement will find him out, be cannot, nor ſhall not eſcape it. And now my dear friends, I ſhall clearly and innocently ſignifie unto you why I do publiſh theſe things; Not in enmity, God is my Witneſs, I have no prejudice in my heart againſt the man, but becauſe the Lord hath laid it upon me, and I dare not diſobey the Lord herein. I could have been willing to have born it all, and have buried all theſe things in the Land of everlaſting Oblivion, if the God of my life had not laid it upon me; for I take no pleaſure in laying open of any mans nakedneſs or weakneſs, or diſcovering any mans offences, crimes or tranſgreſſions, nor in the publication of ſuch things; but I ſee that God is juſt in all his ways &amp; works,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46848:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>and will render to man a juſt recompence of reward according to his workes ſo that as <hi>G F,</hi> hath been very active in ſearching after the knowledge of the failings and offences of others, and in publiſhing of them, and in uſing ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards the offendors, now it is the will and pleaſure of the juſt God to have his offences made manifeſt and publiſhed; &amp; herein this Scripture comes to be fulfilled, <hi>There is nothing hid, that shall not be revealed; what is done in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, shall be revealedon the houſe top, &amp;c.</hi> So that dear Friends, ſtand ſingle in the naked truth, and in the impartial judgement, and you will ſee that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting and the publication of theſe things concerning this man, is juſt at the hand of the righteous God, and mine, who hath no other end in it, but to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the mind of the Lord, who wil make manifeſt the hidden things of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and bring to light that which hath been veiled in obſcurity, that nothing may ſtand before him but purity and naked ſimplicity in his choſen people: And whereas <hi>George Fox</hi> hath called himſelf the Son of God, and alſo ſaid, <hi>I am the Seed,</hi> which he might as well have ſaid, I am Chriſt; (for we know that the Seed is Chriſt) I do deſire Friends to judge impartially of his fruits, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no the Son or Seed of God ever brought forth ſuch things as theſe that follows? And whether or no ſuch have not been, and are yet deceived, who have eſteemed, and do eſteem him infallible?</p>
            <p>And though he hath been in his day and time ſerviceable in the work of the Lord, yet that will not ſave him from judgement in the day of his tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So long as he ſtood innocent and faithful, God honored him with the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his preſence, and proſpered his work in his hand, and he was ſeen by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the Light of righteouſneſs, to be a glorious inſtrument, and had high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of me &amp; many others in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and he was exceeding honorable at that time, and ſo long as he did abide in the perfect zeal of God's glory, &amp; continue and keep in the innocency of the Lambs life, in the true diſcerning and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he had (as he was worthy) double honor; but ſince he hath ſought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt himſelf and throw down others to ſet up himfelf in the higheſt place in the ſeat of God, to rule as Lord over God's Heritage, his glory hath faded, and he ſuffered to be enſnar'd, &amp; to fall into divers temptations, as hereafter wil at large appear, that man's weakneſs may appear, &amp; his glory be ſtained, that God alone may have the glory of his own work, <hi>who is jealous of his honor, and will not give his glory to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is ſeen in the Light of Divine glory, that many eminent inſtruments in the work of Reformation, have brought ſhame &amp; confuſion upon themſelves in ſeeking to exalt themſelves over the people which have had a high eſteem of them, and looked upon them above their places, which hath kindled the wrath of God againſt them, who once employed them in his ſervice: Therefore O <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> give thou the honor and the glory unto thy God alone, and to his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only do thou ſubmit, leſt thou be charged with the guilt of this ſin in over-valuing or too high eſtimation of ſome ſuch inſtruments as God hath employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his ſervice, through affection (and the undervaluing of others through diſ-affection) that thou give not the glory, honor &amp; praiſe to the creature, that properly and wholly belongeth to the Creator, who is over all, God bleſſed for ever; the deſire of my ſoul is, that this ſin may not be found in thee, nor laid to thy charge: The Lord hath ſaid in the zeal of his own glory, <hi>That all the idols of the earth ſhall be abolished, and that the haughilneſs of man shall be laid low;</hi> ſo that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46848:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>all men, though never ſo high in eſteem, that ſeek after their own private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt (and not the good of others) &amp; through ſubtilty and policy ſeek to uſurp Authority over the Conſciences of God's people, &amp; to enthrone themſelves in his Judgement-ſeat, to give forth Legal Preſcriptions, &amp; to enjoin the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of any external form of practiſe, ſuch the God of Heaven will abaſe &amp; throw down, and make them as contemptible in the eyes of the moſt innocent in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as ever they have been honorable. Therefore, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> beware of theſe things, leſt the Lord of glory break forth in his fury, and turn his hand againſt thee, &amp; ſcatter thee amongſt the <hi>Heathen,</hi> as he did <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, who through diſobedience and ambition provoked him to wrath. This warning is in pure love, and in tender compaſſion to your immortal ſouls, and according to the command of God, and the true motion of his eternal Spirit. And now I ſhal proceed to lay to the line of true Judgement, the ſeveral crimes &amp; offences of <hi>G.</hi> F. and do call to him to anſwer to his charge through judgement and publike confeſſion, or otherwiſe according to righteous judgement and juſtice to come to a hearing &amp; due examination before ſome ſound Friends in a publike Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which may be named &amp; ordered for that purpoſe, where he may have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to clear himſelf if he can, of, or from any of the things charged againſt him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thou <hi>G.F.</hi> ſent Papers with thy hand at them, throughout the ſeveral Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the ſeveral Counties, for friends to nominate and appoint ſuch as they eſteemed ſit for the place of <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> and to ſend their names to <hi>London</hi> to be preſented to the then preſent Power to be commiſſionated by them, which was in direct oppoſition to the doctrine of <hi>William Dewsbury</hi> who ſaid publikely in many Aſſemblies, <hi>That he had a command from God to declare and publish among friends (as many are Witneſſes) that there should not be a man in Iſrael to rule one over another, but that the rule and authoriry of man should be overturned, &amp; Chriſt alone rule in the hearts and ſpirits of his people.</hi> Now I deſire that Truth in all may judge whether that this would not have been great confuſion in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> if the Lord had not croſſed the purpoſe of <hi>G.F.</hi> and fruſtrated his end &amp; intentions in this particular, as alſo have brought great ſufferings upon friends, being fond in the place of <hi>Magiſtracy:</hi> As alſo this may truly ſignifie, that he had an end to himſelf, and a ſecret purpoſe in his heart as to exalt himſelf in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Nation; for if he had perfected his purpoſe in getting Friends up in the ſeat of Juſtice, it might truly be ſuppoſed that he would have ſet himſelf over them, &amp; that they ſhould have acted nothing but through or by him &amp; his order; &amp; this is clear, that it <hi>William Dewsbury</hi> had a command from God to cry down the Rule and Government of man, <hi>George Fox</hi> had none to ſet it up.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Letter went forth in his Name with his hand at it, or the Letters of his Name, for <hi>all that had been Officers and Souldier in the Army, that were put forth upon the account of truth, should ſend up their names to London to be preſentod to the then preſent Power, that they might be returned into their reſpective places;</hi> which the Light of truth in many judged &amp; condemned; &amp; there were many amongſt them &amp; is at this day, that could not, nor cannot bear a carnal ſword for conſcience-ſake; therefore conſider whither this man would have led people, if his purpoſe had not failed: &amp; if he had accompliſhed this thing, &amp; friends had been ſound in actual Arms at this Powers coming, it might have cauſed the ruine &amp; deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many innocent people; but bleſſed be the God of peace &amp; love, who ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the iſſue of that deſign: But this alſo clearly evidenceth, that there was a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret intention of the uſurpation of external Government.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:46848:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>3. He ſent a paper to judge <hi>Iohn Hall</hi> upon a lying report, as was proved, &amp; poſitively charged that upon him which he was clear from; upon which publike falſe accuſation and judgement, according to <hi>George Fox</hi>'s own Law, he ought to make confeſſion, and to own publike judgement upon it, being a publike Fact: And this the truth requires of him, to ſatisfie his own Law in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; for he ought to do himſelf to others, as he hath done by them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He judged an innocent woman <hi>ſane Stoakes,</hi> as a carnal Whore, ſent Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with falſe Accuſations amongſt friends, to reproach &amp; render her contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible, to ſtop the teſtimony of truth God had manifeſted in her; as alſo he would not ſuffer her to be aſſiſted in her journey to <hi>Rome,</hi> where ſhe was commanded of God to go, which ſhewed his envy end uncharitableneſs, and alſo the want of diſcerning, who could not ſee her ſervice for the Lord there, which ſhe faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully performed, notwithſtanding his envy againſt her: And for this notorious publike crime in defaming her, and not aſſiſting or permitting her to be aſsiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the publike ſtock provided and ordered for that purpoſe, he ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo according to his own Law to acknowledge the ſame upon his knees, &amp; own judgement publikely in all places where he hath defamed her, which his own Law requireth of him, and the truth cannot own his Authority, until he hath ſatisfied and fulfilled his own Law in this particular.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The ſaid <hi>G.F.</hi> ſent <hi>George Baily</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> who dyed in priſon, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to me <hi>he had no command from God to go in his ſervice, neither did he know any particular place to go to in France;</hi> whoſe blood is, &amp; wil be required at his hand.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The ſaid <hi>G.F.</hi> contrary to the principles of truth proſeſſed by us, he vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and juſtified the practiſe of Water-baptiſm in <hi>Humphrey Wooldridge,</hi> who in water baptized a woman one of his diſciples he ſent forth to miniſter; which was a publike fact, and required publike acknowledgement and judgement ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own Rule and Law.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The ſame <hi>G.F.</hi> when he is in <hi>London,</hi> takes upon him the place of God, and orders thoſe he accounts Miniſters in his will, and ſends them to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Meetings in and about <hi>London,</hi> ſaying to them particularly, (to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) <hi>Thou muſt go to ſuch a place;</hi> and to another, <hi>Thou muſt go to ſuch a place, or ſuch a place is ordered for thee;</hi> and thither they muſt go, whether they have any command or motion from God to go or no; and in his abſence leaves one of his moſt eminent ſervants to order the reſt eſteemed Miniſters in his place on the firſt days, who alſo orders them by word of mouth, or gives them a piece of paper; which thing the ſoul of the righteous God lothes, and the ſeed of his life bears teſtimony againſt, for the which he muſt come to judgement.</p>
            <p n="8">8. He ſent forth <hi>Milborough Smith</hi> into the Miniſtry, and bid go and be a Mother in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when ſhe was with a Baſtard-Child, and was ſhortly after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered of it; which ſhews his inſufficiency and want of diſcerning to officiate ſuch a place, as alſo his fallibility and uſurpation, which is likewiſe for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like judgement.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The ſaid <hi>G.</hi> F. in envy writ a paper in pretence of an Anſwer to a Book of innocent <hi>John Perrots,</hi> called <hi>Vnity and Amity,</hi> which he ſent amongſt friends in the time of his perſecution, which was judged by the eternal Power and Life of God in ſeveral of his ſuffering ſervants: which was alſo a publike fact for publike judgement amongſt friends. And here he hath turned his hand againſt the choſen and annointed of God, which wil in the end prove to his own hurt.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:46848:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>10. <hi>George Fox</hi> in his Book tituled, <hi>The Honor amongſt the Iews,</hi> calls the Hat <hi>an earthly thing, and a thing below the Worship of God, and the dignity of a man,</hi> and ſpeaks much againſt the putting off the Hat; but now he goes to ſet it up as part of God's Worſhip, and ſaith. <hi>He hath unity with none but ſuch as put off their Hats in prayer:</hi> So makes it clearly manifeſt, that he is changeable and fallible, and that his unity ſtands in an earthly thing, and in that he confeſſeth is below the worſhip of God; and here he would ſet up a form, and tye the Lords free people to the performance of an external practiſe, contrary to the liberty of the free Spirit of Life, which ought in all things to order and exerciſe Gods choſen Remnant, who are only and alone to be ordered in the performance of all duties and practiſes, according to its leading and immediate motion, which is alſo to be denied and judged out, at the entrance or inlet of idolatry into the Church, which all impoſitions and penal injunctions lead unto.</p>
            <p n="11">11. He alſo reviled and reproached me, and judged and condemned me in ſeveral papers which he hath ſpread up and down the Countreys amongſt Friends, for the very ſame thing which he acknowledged (in <hi>Gerard Roberts</hi> Chamber) two yeers or more ago, that the power had remitted; which ſhews his envy and confuſion: But this his end in ſo doing (as the clear-ſighted in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> may diſcern) he thought thereby to raiſe prejudice in Friends againſt me, that they might not receive me nor my teſtimony, that ſo I might be quite diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and the ſtrength of truths teſtimony God hath manifeſted in me, might be taken away, that ſo I might have no power to call him to an account for theſe things God hath laid upon me to charge againſt him: But bleſſed be the Name of the pure God for ever, who hath given, and doth give me ſtrength and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in his truth to clear my Conſcience in obeying his wil in this thing, which in the end wil come heavy upon him.</p>
            <p n="12">12. His cowardlineſs in ſhrinking in the time of perſecution, his ſhifting from place to place both in this City and Countrey, to ſhun a priſon, or to avoid ſuffering, is for judgement, many in <hi>Iſrael</hi> took notice of it; where there was danger, he ſent others, and would not go himſelf: He ſent <hi>Thomas Richardſon</hi> to <hi>Ely,</hi> but refuſed to go himſelf when Friends deſired him; and the man was put in priſon, and would have given it under his hand, if friends, would have ſuffered him, that he knew not whether the Light of ſalvation was in every man or no. And ſuch dark ignorant men he ſends forth to burden the Seed in Friends; yet they will cry up his Name, and receive Orders from him, and be his ſervants or ſlaves, which the Light of pure wiſdom diſowns and judges, and he muſt come to the bar of Juſtice, and receive the ſentence of condemnation for ſuch things; for the truth will not, nor ſuch as live in it, juſtifie him in theſe or the like practiſes.</p>
            <p n="13">13. He ſent papers of enmity, and ſet his ſervantr on work in <hi>Barbadoes</hi> and <hi>Virginia,</hi> to judge and reproach innocent <hi>John Perrot, Jane Stoakes</hi> and <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Harris,</hi> who were moved to go in the ſervice of the Lord, which is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to truth, love and mercy; which practiſe is alſo for perpetual judgement.</p>
            <p n="14">14. The ſaid <hi>George Fox</hi> did cauſe <hi>John Fretwell, Chriſtopher Gilburn,</hi> and <hi>James Naylor,</hi> with ſeveral others, to go down upon their knees before him publikely amongſt Friends (which is groſs idolatry) and there and then upon their knees to make their confeſſion, and own judgement upon what he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt them, before he would own them, or receive them into unity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46848:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Friends; which practiſe the Seed of God lothes and abominates, and it is but according to his own Rule and Law that he upon his knees ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to, and own publike judgement upon what is charged againſt him; for if a man make a Law, he ought to obſerve and keep it.</p>
            <p n="15">15. His writing and ſpeaking againſt Pulpits and high-places upheld by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and allowing ſuch like things in our own Meeting-places, which he hath been told of, is for judgement; and his ſeveral forms concerning Marriage: Firſt, He ſent on this Orders to the ſeveral Churches, to publiſh Marriages three times publikely in meetings, and now he ſends forth another to contradict that, to lay it before Men-friends Meetings, as alſo before Women friends Meetings, and they muſt have their approbation before they take one another; and this ſhews his chargeable ſpirit, and his fallibility; and all theſe his preſcribed Laws and impoſed forms are out of the truth, and with it judged; yet the Marriage in the Lord is owned to be lawful and honorable, and publication alſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the immediate motion of the Spirit of Love and Life, that joins in one, and makes of two one fleſh.</p>
            <p n="16">16. The ſaid <hi>G. F.</hi> hath allowed [after notice] of <hi>John Moon's</hi> going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the Miniſtry, and hath ſent him abroad as a Miniſter ſince he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied lyes publikely amongſt friends, ſaying and affirming, that there ſhould not be a wicked Magiſtrate in <hi>England</hi> within two years time, which is near expired: And further ſaid, That if that which he then ſpoke did not come to paſs, the Lord never ſpoke by him: Which I lay to the line of righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all friends, to judge of this matter, whether or no the lying ſpirit ought to miniſter in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yea or nay. Surely, ſurely the juſt God wil plead with ſome for theſe and the like things ſuffered and countenance in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. His being ſhut up in a room in <hi>Newgate-Market</hi> with <hi>Margaret Fell,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral hours, and none ſuffered to come into them, though ſeveral endeavoured it, hath not the ſavour of honeſtly in it; but I ſhall leave that to the Lord to judge of, who will reward them according to their works. And it is alſo report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongſt friends, that the ſaid <hi>George Fox</hi> &amp; <hi>Margaret Fell</hi> did ſo carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves each to other, and walk ſo unſeemly and undiſcreetly at the Houſe of <hi>Elizabeth Trott</hi> when they lay there, that ſhe queſtioned their honeſty, and was weary of their company; and what this doth ſignifie, let truth innocency judge.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The ſaid <hi>George Fox</hi> contrary to the doctrine and practice of Chriſt and the Saints, hath gone himſelf amongſt friends in and about this City, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, reproach and backbite the innocent, and alſo hath warned, and ſent his ſervants to warn friends for entertaining ſuch as he diſ-affects and envies, ſo would not leave them a place to reſt in, but would even force them with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence from the truth, if the Lord by his mighty power did not preſerve them: As likewiſe in other places he hath gone about in the ſame manner, which pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe is for eternal judgement and condemnation: It was not, nor is not the work of the true Spirit in the Saints, to hate and envy their Enemies, nor to purſue them from place to place with falſe railing accuſations, much leſſe the people of God, who in a large meaſure have ſuffered in innocency for his Name and Truth, as <hi>G.F.</hi> hath done, and now doth, which is a true ſign, or ſignal teſtimony that he is not in the true Spirit, the Spirit of Love, but in the contrary, which is not to bear rule, nor predominate in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> It is, and was
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46848:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Doctrine of Chriſt and the Saints to love their enemies to gain ſouls to God with meekneſs and love, and alſo their practiſe to reſtore or regain ſuch as were enſnared through temptation, in all tenderneſs and bowels of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion, and likewiſe to ſeek after the loſt ſheep of the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to fetch them back into the ſold of reſt: They did not as <hi>G.</hi> F. doth, drive by force a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſuch as he looks upon as gone aſtray, which clearly proveth that he is out of the power of the healing, reſtoring Spirit, in the devouring nature, which forceth me (with many others) to deny his Authority, and to bear a living te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony for God againſt his works, practiſes, uſurpation and Lordly Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who ſeeks in the ſtrength of his ſubtilty to ſet up himſelf in the ſeat of Chriſt, to rule over the Conſciences of God's choſen Remnant, which is no other but the Sun of the Morning, which hath not kept his firſt habitation, which the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> wil dethrone and caſt down.</p>
            <p>And this I teſtifie in the Name of the Lord, in a clear diſcerning, and perfect underſtanding, that <hi>G.F.</hi> hath turned his hand againſt, and ſtruck at the moſt glorious appearance of the life of God theſe ſeveral years, in the deareſt of God's people; and it is not only the Hat, and the other things reported amongſt friends, which cauſeth <hi>G.F.</hi> to turn againſt J. <hi>P.</hi> but becauſe of that beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful life God hath manifeſt in him, which to the ſimple and innocent-hearted in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> did appear more amiable and glorious then his Miniſtration; &amp; becauſe that the virtue and ſweetneſs of the clear life of God manifeſt in J. <hi>P.</hi> drew the Virgins in <hi>Iſrael</hi> after it, therefore G.<hi>F.</hi> hath ſought, and doth ſeek with violence to deſtroy that which is moſt excellent and glorious, that he may have the honor and glory to himſelf, which many in <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Light of truth have ſeen, and do ſee; and ſince the ſpirit of <hi>Saul</hi> entred G: <hi>F.</hi> behold how he hath loſt his ſtrength, and how his glory hath faded; <hi>He that hath an eye to ſee, let him ſee, and an ear to hear, let him hear, and alſo he that can receive it, let him, this is true and faithful teſtimony.</hi> And mark furthermore, he doth not only purſue and ſeek to deſtroy the life of God in J.P. and to hinder the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony thereof from going forth in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but alſo in all ſuch as own, love and affect his innocent life; which manifeſts clearly to the impartial underſtanding in Iſrael, <hi>That he ſeeks to deſtroy the Son and Heir, to make the inheritance his own: ſo ſeeks to exalt himſelf, and after his own glory, and not to exalt the Lord and his alone glory: But the Lord of Life and glory is ariſing in his mighty power, in the zeal of his own honor and glory, and will ſtain the glory of all flesh, and throw down, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly overturn the rule and government of man in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and will ſet up his own go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and heavenly authority over all, in the hearts and conſciences of his choſen people, and they to his Scepter alone shall bow, and shall not be enſlaved through the uſurpation of ambitious man.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By one of the deſpiſed Remnant, who ſets up no man, but ſeeks only the exaltation of God's alone glory, and honors all men in the Lord, and owns all men in their places, known by this Name,</hi> JOHN HARWOOD,</signed>
               <dateline>London <date>the 8th. of the 6th. Mon. 1663.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
